hi John I diligently observed the eight
precepts and I believe I'm putting in
sincere effort however a persistent
thought troubles me
the notion that using or having money
might impede my progress or purity
why is refraining from money one of the
higher precepts the the 10 precepts are
how does abstaining from it contribute
to spiritual freedom
what's inherently wrong with money
because as long as I I use it for good
and refrain from harmful actions and
could money be a hindrance to Awakening
in short no of course not uh no it was a
it was a practical reason for that
precept when the uh when the order grew
when the uh when the order grew
basically uh you know like you have
monks on their own
ordaining here and there through various
teachers uh living roughly
uh living roughly
traveling around having access to money
meant having access to Central things if
that's where the mind their mind would
turn towards
so it was uh it was a a practical rule
to prevent The Temptations for new monks
for monks that are not developed amongst
they are not established in virtue
because uh even today as well you could
think about it like if you were to have
Euro money without any supervision
without anybody else knowing how it's
being spent if the mind is not developed
you might give in to desires and get
this or get that
but that's again if you are not
developed if you're not interested in
practice if you're slacking if you're if
you're regressing
um so in a similar fashion it was like a
you know the rule about not storing food
again it was for those who were not
developed to prevent them from kind of going lacks
to prevent them from kind of going lacks
and and proliferating towards sensuality
not because it's in and of itself an
impediment for enlightenment I mean
broke that rule he was an arhand who was
storing food not because out of Desire
or craving but because the village was
too poor and they couldn't they they
would still feed him but he felt bad for
taking food every day because they don't
have enough for themselves so if he had
the leftover he would put it aside to it
next day so he doesn't take it from them
but then the Buddha said no it's an
offense you got to convey because again
from a practical standpoint of an
managing the order of monks it could
give rise that allowance to like many
monks they were not our hands they were
not developed could basically because of
that start slacking and so on
so the money was the same he said who
has access to money has access to the
five codes of sensuality
and you know back in the day like you
could have engaged with those things
without anybody ever knowing because
there were so many different Summoners
different brahmins different types
somebody had money somebody not nobody
would have bet an eyelid so to speak
so they would have made that rule just
to prevent those who are not developed
who are still in training to to kind of
fall into that trap
so basically it applies to the monks so
if you have withdrawn yourself from
everything else uh
given up the household life
having that kind of direct unchecked
access to money can become the
impediment there there and then but if
you're a householder
uh keeping the precepts a preset great
practicing within that uh again if you
keep the precepts no amount of money can
become an obstacle for you unless you
break the precepts through money
unless you start or sense restraint if
you are well restrained restraining your
senses restraining your craving again no
amount of gold or money can make you
lose that perspective
but as I said as if you are like from
the standpoint of managing an order
if something like that happens you have
to look at a bigger picture
and then say ah no because again for
most of these new monks or something it
could result in issues so let's just not
even go there
but this is not that it's not the same
context it's not the same it's not the
same starting point
what about that whole you know once if
you have money okay you have access to
Central pleasures of all kinds
um
but you you also
or some people would have a sense of
control of safety of safety well yeah
but see that's money just reveals that I
was gonna I was gonna say that next so
if that person was the question I don't
know if they're a monk or a lemon
basically is there a monk liposite a
presumably person yeah so money would
not be an obstacle for other hand chip
being a householder would be an obstacle
for our energy
but again if you're not even a Sota Bana
or anagami from that point of view I
wouldn't worry about obstacle last
obstacle for other hardship develop
everything else that you can
as opposed to now taking too much and
not even doing the first step properly
and that's the reason why as I said
money would reveal that sense of control
sense of control that's inherently bound
with the household life
I come as I please I go as I please I'm
My Own Boss nobody tells me what to do
uh nobody tells me how to walk how to
talk how to eat how to carry my ball how
to relate to people I could just do what
I want because I'm an individual I have
my own place my own apartment my own
house I'm My Own Boss
and that inherently is bound with the
sense of control and sense of safety
that comes uncovery that's why a Layman
cannot become another hunt from that
point of view not because it's so
magical energy preventing him but
because to that degree he's still not
relinquishing that sense of control
that's founded upon his sense of I am
so it's not like I need to magically put
the robes on in order to become an
arhand then no I need to relinquish the
household life regardless of what I wear
I need to relinquish that fundamental
control that I've been living through my
whole life
and that's really the issue that not the
money so if you're keeping the eight presets
so if you're keeping the eight presets
and a diligent in regard to it and
diligent in sense restraint develop the
right view free yourself from sensuality
within that money will then just be a
practical tool you're using for survival
because you're not you're not going
around on Pender part or getting food by
donors and so on
uh and then like if you want to really
become another hunt and you don't have
anybody depending on you in your life
they would die if you leave and so on
how it goes back in the suitors then go
for today and give up the money as well
and there you go
but now it's like worrying about what
type of car do I have when you haven't
even found a horse
so it's it's you know one step at a time